                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <filename>fcs_isa.c</filename>/<filename>fcs_isa.h</filename> - 
                            Short for Indirect State Allocation, this module 
                            allocated vectors of states, each one is of constant 
                            size.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
        <section id="scm_maintaining_a_list_of_modules">
            <title>Maintaining a list of Modules</title>
            <para>
                The script <filename>gen_makefile.pl</filename> maintains a 
                list of modules and headers across all makefiles that are 
                distributed as part of Freecell Solver.
            </para>
            <para>
                Notice that the Win32 makefile is generated from a hard-coded
                template, while the other makefiles are read and modified by it.
            </para>
        </section>

        If a development version is present, it is checked out of the CVS,
        packed into an archive, and placed on the site with a link in the
        downloads page.

        
            <para>
                The site generation process also generates a zip archive of the 
                latest stable version so it can be used to automatically 
                compile the Win32 binary.            
            </para>

        <section id="scm_freecell_solver_config">
            <title>freecell-solver-config</title>
            <para>
                The autoconf process creates a freecell-solver-config program that
                can be used as an aid in programs wishing to compile and link
                against &fcs;. It is generated from freecell-solver-config.in by
                the configure script and is installed system-wide.            
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="scm_win32_binary">
            <title>The Win32 Binary</title>
            <para>
                The Win32 binary is compiled by a batch file placed on the site 
                and found in the CVS in the location 
                <ulink url="http://cvs.berlios.de/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/fc-solve/fc-solve/site/wml/src/win32_build/bootstrap/build.bat">/fc-solve/site/wml/src/win32_build/bootstrap/built.bat</ulink>
            </para>
            <para>
                This script should be placed on a Windows NT 4.0 and above 
                computer that has the Microsoft Visual Studio environment 
                installed. It should be placed in a directory containing only it 
                and the curl.exe executable from 
                <ulink url="http://fc-solve.berlios.de/win32_build/">the same location</ulink>.
            </para>

            <para>
                What it does is the following:
            </para>

            <para>
                <orderedlist>                
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Download zip.exe and unzip.exe from the static sub-directory.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Download fcs.zip from the dynamic sub-directory.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Unpack fcs.zip.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                   
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Determine its version number and record it in a 
                            variable.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>

                            Compile Freecell Solver.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Place the relevant files in a directory structure by 
                            copying them.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>               
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Create a zip archive of them.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>          
                </orderedlist>
            </para>        
        </section>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Packs</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>

                            See <link 
                                linkend="term_state_packs">State Packs</link>.

                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
        
                <varlistentry id="term_state_packs">
                    <term>State Packs</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            An allocation of states. Each state pack is a buffer in
                            memory, that contain an array of states. Each buffer
                            remains at a constant memory location, but more buffers
                            are allocated as necessary. The implementation of State
                            packs reside in the files
                            <filename>fcs_isa.c</filename> and
                            <filename>fcs_isa.h</filename>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Secondary Hash Value</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>

                            A hash value that is calculated for every state
                            that is not used to determine the location of the
                            element in the hash table, but that is used for
                            comparison.  That is done in order to avoid
                            needlessly comparing two different states with the
                            same hash value.

                        </para>
                        <para>

                            Freecell Solver uses a 32-bit primary hash value.
                            As such it is susceptible to the birthday paradox
                            starting at about 2<superscript>16</superscript>. A
                            secondary hash value with extra 32-bits ensures a
                            collision of both hash values will only happen at
                            around 2<superscript>32</superscript> states, which
                            is much more states than most 32-bit systems can
                            handle.

                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

