<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oa
sis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"[]> -->
<!-- This comment is meant to settle gvim -->

<chapter id="techniques">
    <title>Interesting Techniques Used throughout the Code</title>
    <section id="technique_state_representation">
        <title>State Representation</title>
        <para>
            As can be seen in <filename>state.h</filename>, &fcs; 
            supports three ways to represent a state:
        </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Debug States</emphasis> - 
                        in this configuration, stack counters, 
                        and cards are represented as 32-bit quantities. 
                        This configuration consumes a lot of memory, and is 
                        the slowest of the three. It is however useful for 
                        debugging, as the debugger will display the state 
                        data-structure very nicely.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Compact States</emphasis> - in this 
                        configuration the data is one buffer of chars,
                        where each card and each stack counter are 
                        represented as one character, and each freecell and 
                        foundation is one char too.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Determining the locations of every card is done 
                        using offset calculation.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This configuration consumes much less memory than 
                        Debug States, but it doesn't scale well to games 
                        where the stacks can contain a lot of cards.
                        The reason is that every stack be of a fixed size
                        (so offset would be determined by means of 
                        multiplication).
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This configuration used to be the fastest for 
                        limited stack games such as Freecell. After 
                        &fcs; 2.6.x, it seems that Indirect Stack States 
                        has become slightly faster than it, too.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Indirect Stack States</emphasis> - 
                        in this configuration 
                        each stack is a pointer to a stack in memory. 
                        The stacks are also collected and there is one copy
                        of each stack organization (say [KS QH 6H]) in 
                        memory. Since a pointer to a stack uniquely 
                        identifies a stack, the states can be compared by
                        comparing their memory contents.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This is now the default configuration, and in the 
                        2.5.x development tree, many enhancments were done to 
                        optimize it. It was benchmarked to be slightly faster 
                        than Compact States, even for games like freecell.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="technique_indirect_stack_states_algorithms">
        <title>Indirect Stack States Algorithms</title>
        <para>
            The stacks are kept in their own stack collection in the 
            freecell_solver_instance struct. When a test wishes to 
            create a derived states, it first copies the state, and then 
            marks the flags of all the stacks as cleared. (check 
            <symbol>(*Mark STACKS_COW_CLEAR *)</symbol> in the code).
        </para>
        <para>
            Later on when a stack is changed, its flag is set, and a 
            stack is copied to a hard-thread wide indirect stacks buffer 
            and modified there. (check (*Mark STACKS_COW_COPY_STACK*) ).
        </para>
        <para>
            The check_and_add_state function then, when checking a 
            new state, ignores those stacks whose flag was not set, 
            and collects the stacks whose flag was set.
            ( <symbol>(*Mark STACKS_COW_CACHING*)</symbol> ). The 
            memory for the collected stacks is allocated compactly in 
            a segment, where one stack starts after the other
            (check <filename>alloc.c</filename> and <filename>alloc.h</filename>). 
            If the stack was found in the collection the memory that was 
            allocated is freed for use by future stacks).
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="technique_extended_states">
        <title>Extended States</title>
        <para>
            For each position in the game graph, Freecell Solver maintains a 
            data structure that identifies it called 
            <type>fcs_state_t</type>. This contains the cards in the 
            stacks and the freecells, and the value of the foundations. The 
            stacks and freecells are uniquely sorted to avoid states that 
            are identical except for a different permutation of the stacks 
            or the freecells.
        </para>
        <para>
            <type>fcs_state_t</type> is the first member of
            <type>fcs_state_with_locations_t</type>, that defines some
            other data. The real locations of the stacks and freecells are
            stored there for instance, as well as some graph information. See
            Canonization and Normalization in the terminology.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="technique_the_states_graph_and_its_use">
        <title>The States Graph and its Use</title>
        <para>
            When a brand new state is discovered its parent is assigned to be
            the state from which it is derived. (check <symbol>(*Mark
                STATE_PARENT*)</symbol>). Its depth is assigned to be the depth
            of the parent + 1. There is a command line option
            (--reparent-states) that specifies that if an existing state whose
            depth is higher than the depth of state it was derived from + 1 is
            reached, then its parent would be re-assigned.
        </para>
        <para>
            An extended state has a num_active_children counter that 
            specifies how many of those states that consider it their parent 
            were still not marked as dead ends. If this counter reaches 0, 
            this state also becomed inactive.
        </para>

        <para>
            The state has a vector of flags called scan_visited, that specifies
            if a given scan has visited it yet. If it is a complete scan it can
            also mark it as dead end should it:
        </para>

        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Recurse out of it if it's a DFS scan.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Find that it has no derived states if it is a 
                        Best-First Search scan.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            If it is marked as dead end, then its parent's counter would be 
            incremented. If the latter is zero, the process may continue to 
            the grand parent and so forth.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="technique_life_cycle_of_a_f_s_instance_t">
        <title>The Life-Cycle of a freecell_solver_instance_t</title>
        <para>
            A <type>freecell_solver_instance_t</type> is allocated by 
            <filename>lib.c</filename> to start solving a board. The logic
            of solving a board is present in <filename>intrface.c</filename> 
            while the stubs to use it are implemented in 
            <filename>lib.c</filename>.
        </para>
        <para>
            After an instance is allocated, it should be paramterized to
            specify how it will solve the board. Afterwards, 
            <function>freecell_solver_init_instance()</function> should
            be called. After that, 
            <function>freecell_solver_solve_instance()</function> should
            be called for the first time, and 
            <function>freecell_solver_resume_instance()</function> afterwards.
            (these functions solve until they reach a limit of iterations 
            number.)
        </para>
        <para>
            If one would like to use the instance to solve another board, it is
            possible to recycle it by calling
            <function>freecell_solver_recycle_instance()</function>.  This will
            keep its configuration but free all its associated resources, and
            thus will not require parsing the command line again.
        </para>
        <para>
            The function that calls the actual scans is 
            <function>run_hard_thread()</function>, which is called from 
            within <function>freecell_solver_resume_instance()</function>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="technique_compact_allocation">
        <title>Compact Allocation</title>
        <para>
            Most resources that are allocated arbitrarily in &fcs; are
            allocated in a compact manner. I.e: instead of being individually
            malloced, they are allocated in segments and placed one after the
            other. The segments are dynamically allocated and kept at a fixed
            location in memory. If more memory is needed, another segment is
            allocated.
        </para>
        <para>
            There are two modules whose code is used to achieve this end:
        </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <filename>fcs_isa.c</filename>/<filename>fcs_isa.h</filename> - 
                        Short for Indirect State Allocation, this module 
                        allocated vectors of states, each one is of constant 
                        size.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <filename>alloc.c</filename>/<filename>alloc.h</filename> -
                        allocates blocks of arbitrary size in a compact manner.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            Both of these modules support releasing the last allocated block
            and the last one alone.
        </para>        
        <para>
            Compact allocation is used for the following resources.
        </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>States</emphasis> - using fcs_isa. A derived 
                        state is allocated using the hard thread's allocator, 
                        and it is modified with the appropriate moves. If it 
                        is found to have already existed, it is released. 
                        Else, it is kept and a pointer to it can be found 
                        in the states collection.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Card stacks</emphasis> - if a card stack was 
                        modified, it is compactly allocated (see 
                        <symbol>(*Mark COMPACT_ALLOC_CARD_STACKS*)</symbol> ), 
                        before one checks to see if it is present in the 
                        stacks collection. If it was found there, its memory 
                        is released. Else, it is kept there.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Move stacks</emphasis> - 
                        the move stacks leading to the parent are compactly 
                        allocated (see (*Mark COMPACT_ALLOC_MOVE_STACKS*)).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Hash Elements</emphasis> - The elements of 
                        the hash linked lists are compactly allocated with a 
                        specialized hash allocator.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>


<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-parent-document: "fcs_arch_doc.xml"
End:
-->

